a question that comes up
or that i see a lot is
how to deal with hateful people
matter doesn't seem to work no
well as we as we said in other talks
the first thing you do well the first
thing you have to do
when you're experiencing hate towards
somebody like i mean somebody might be hateful to
like i mean somebody might be hateful to
you but you are experiencing aversion
towards that experience
you don't want people to be hateful
because then
you end up being reversed and hateful or
same if
if you're experiencing lust and greed
the first thing you have to do
is not act out of it so if somebody is
hateful towards you
you should not be hateful towards them
by body
by speech mentally you might not be able
to help yourself to have bad
thoughts and so on but only after you
have been accomplished
sufficiently enough in a non-acting
out of hate regardless of what hate
comes your way
not speaking out of hate regardless of
what hate comes your way
then you will be able to do something
about on the level of your mind
so the problem the reason why matter
doesn't work is because well it doesn't
work on that level
people would think oh i'm experiencing
hate i'm full of aversion
let me do mata but they do it so to get
rid of the aversion
to get rid of the experience that's
unpleasant so all they want to do
metaphor is because it's unpleasant
otherwise and an acting out of this pleasure
and an acting out of this pleasure
that's why you're still a verse because
you you keep acting when things are
you keep trying to get rid of the
displeasure because you're reversed to
it
that's why you perpetuate your attitude
of perversion
so that's why the buddha would often say
the words
abuse of others insults and so on
needs to be endured like you would in
your heat
cold bad weather and so on
when you like you don't you know
like when it's cold you don't get angry
with the winter
you just bear the discomfort sure
you get warmer but you're not full of
aversion i hate
this discomfort because you can't really
i mean you can try but it's
futile because you can't you know you
can't do much about it so you just try
to avoid cold yeah try and avoid hateful
people but don't try to get rid of the
but don't try to get rid of the
discomfort
in a sense of um i'm averse to this so
i'll do everything in my power to not
experience this
no when it arises you have to endure it
so what would be the endurance in terms
of somebody being hateful to you
well not acting back that's the
endurance part
and that's the metaphor well that's the
prerequisite for meta
if you if you have sufficiently not
acted out of your aversion out of your
last towards the world
if you have sufficiently withdrawn
yourself away from the world through
that um through avoiding that unwholesome
um through avoiding that unwholesome
basis for your action
then yeah you're left with just a
recognition of
your own aversion in in regard to this
body experiencing heat cold bad weather
abuse of others others are irrelevant
what's relevant is that you don't want
to bear it here
because a number of times like you can
even see that even without matter when
you were in a good mood and somebody
hateful but hey it doesn't reach you
because you remain impatient you don't
move it's like ah so really that's the root
it's like ah so really that's the root
of the problem i can't stop
world from being hateful if they want
it's just you know
how can you control that but you can
certainly stop yourself from being
affected by that
but the first thing to do is stop acting
out of it stop stop
you know doing stuff in return including
i must do meta amazing
because i can't bear this no first you
have to bear it and it's
that's that's what means being
accomplished in virtue and and restraint
means knowing that you can bear it even
if you don't do anything about it even
if you can't do anything about it
you know for sure well at least i know i
can bear it because i beared it
and then the mind will start to come
down and then the things become clear in
a sense of
i'm not actually a verse towards you i'm
a verse to
this body experiencing discomfort of
elements and hateful speech from
external sort of points of view so
sort of points of view so
that's where the matter begins
self-aversion aversion towards the senses there was
aversion towards the senses there was
non-control towards still it's
discomfort it comes through them and
mind of friendliness as we spoke before
so then even if you're
absolutely violently hateful i'm not
abandoning that
gateway where the problem would arise
for me
from that my problem is not that you're
hateful my problem is if i try to get
rid of this body experience in that hate
but the only reason i will be trying to
get rid of that is if i'm still
cultivating aversion towards it
but now i'm cultivating the mind of
friendliness and benevolence regardless
of what comes this way
so i cannot be a verse so no matter how
much you shout and you're abusive
the body remains oh well i remain
universal towards my own senses
with my own body that are experiencing
all of that hate and elements and so on
yeah and that's the root that you deal
with that's the framework exactly that you
that's the framework exactly that you
you you maintain you protect your mind
like a mother protects your only child
as mata sutra says
you protect your mind on that level like
your precious child protect the mind of
friendliness just there
nothing else will be a problem it
doesn't matter how hateful
and and intense things around get mind
of friendliness first
and that is and that is truly unlimited
state it would be boundless because it's not
it would be boundless because it's not
bound anymore with perceptions of self
or others for that matter
so imagine and then you develop
confidence on the point of
highway robbers as the suitors say can
come and started violently attacking you
with machetes
and your mind of friendliness will still
not change and you know that
this is fearlessness as well doesn't
matter what happens mind friendliness
cannot be affected and that's why it's a
brahmavihara they would have said
somebody cultivates their mind on that
level rebirth in brahma realm is guaranteed
rebirth in brahma realm is guaranteed
because it's just so elevated
so boundless immeasurable elevated
beyond or above
the world well internally above the
gratuitous diversification of
me you mine all that's been perpetuated
not because of some intellectual error
or lack of information but because of
acting out of
senses that pressure you play pleasing
sight sounds multi-touches assail you
you go towards them displeasing smell
sights out their statues are sail you
you try to get rid of them you do matter
you do meditation
but all for the sake of acting out of
senses not developed in regard to your own body
not developed in regard to your own body
that's why you act
because you try to get rid of it so
patient endurance
as we say so often accomplished in
virtue sense restraint needs whatever
whatever practice
or meditation you do or contemplation
this is a non-negotiable basis
accomplished in virtue having like as i
said no no you you develop a knowledge that
no no you you develop a knowledge that
i can endure even if i can't do anything
about it even if i don't know the way
out i can't figure it out things are all
i can't figure it out things are all
crowded i don't understand anything but
used to be so it doesn't matter
how much doubt you know but i can do
because i endured it and i still am
doing it
and that's accomplished in virtue and
then when thing passes which will have
to you realize even in that
instance i didn't act so even more
confidence on account of your virtue
grows even more gladness then comes because
even more gladness then comes because
now you know that even
harder circumstances you still did not
act out of that pressure so that's why
sila first samadhi comes out of it
first samadhi comes out of it
immovability of your mind will come out
of the confidence of silas
that's exactly what it would have
described it's so many ways so many
times realizing that there is no
realizing that there is no
boundary then well sure sure but i don't
want to
get into describing what's after it will
become self-evident what's after if you become
self-evident what's after if you become
accomplished in virtue and stop acting
out of
a version out of agreeable and
disagreeable that's it that's it cultivate don't
that's it that's it cultivate don't
think
that cultivation of that endurance
accomplishment in virtue is somehow
irrelevant that is the practice samadhi is within
that is the practice samadhi is within
that and pineal is within that
not after that so if you're
accomplishing virtue you already have a
basis that contains samadhi and
pineapple
so you never abandon that then i don't i
will not act out of the pressure of the
senses
even if i can't figure it out i will not
act i will sustain it
and they will accomplish it and that's
it